Inventory to the Robert D. Burhans papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert D. Burhans papers
1942-1945
XX096
Hoover Institution Archives
32 manuscript boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 10 envelopes (16.5 linear feet)
Materials relating to activities of the First Special Service Force ("Devil's Brigade") and the 474th Infantry Regiment during World War II including correspondence, field orders, directives, reports, regulations, handbooks, maps, and photographs. Used as research material for the book by R. D. Burhans, The First Special Service Force: A War History of the North Americans, 1942-1944 (Washington, D.C., 1947).
Burhans, Robert D.
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical Note
Colonel, United States Army; member, First Special Service Force, during World War II.
Scope and Content of Collection
Materials relating to activities of the First Special Service Force ("Devil's Brigade") and the 474th Infantry Regiment during World War II including correspondence, field orders, directives, reports, regulations, handbooks, maps, and photographs. Used as research material for the book by R. D. Burhans, The First Special Service Force: A War History of the North Americans, 1942-1944 (Washington, D.C., 1947).
Allied Forces. Special Service Force, 1st.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 474th.; Canada.; United States--Armed Forces.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Italy.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Handbook for military government in Germany (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous notebook (Box 1)
- German town plans, (2 pamphlets) (Box 1)
- The Libyan campaign, 1942; (1 pamphlet) (Box 1)
- Training, 1942-1943; (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Report of operations, Attu, (1 pamphlet) (Box 1)
- Correspondence, casualties, and condolences, 1945; (2 folders, miscellaneous items) (Box 1)
- Civil administration and claims, 1944-1945; (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Anzio Beachhead executive file, 1944; (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Secret telegrams, Amchitka '43, also journal of orders, incidents, etc..., (1 folder, miscellaneous items) (Box 1)
- Historical file (general), (1 folder) (Box 1)
- Kiska, (1 folder) (Box 2)
- Little Kiska, (1 folder) (Box 2)
- Little Kiska, S-2 reports, (1 folder) (Box 2)
- Field Orders, First Special Service Force (FSSF) Part I, Apr 1943-Apr 1944; (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Field Order #1, Landing Force 16.8 secret security, 1 August 1943; (3 folders) (Box 2)
- Equipment, 1943; (1 folder) (Box 2)
- Booklet prescribing clothing, equipment and ammunition, FFSF, 1943 (Box 3)
- II Corps, Dec 1943-Jan 1944; (1 folder) (Box 3)
- 3rd Infantry Division, Mar 1944-June 1945; (1 folder) (Box 3)
- Operational File, 7th Army, July-Sept 1944; (1 folder) (Box 3)
- VI Corps field orders, Jan-May 1944; (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Operation Bruno, FSSF, July-Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 4)
- S.L.O.E. for FSSF, Sept 1943; (1 folder) (Box 4)
- Table of equipment, Oct 1943; (1 folder) (Box 4)
- Difensa, 1-9 Dec 1943; (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Field Order no. 5, FSSF Kiska, 8 Aug 1943; (1 folder) (Box 4)
- Kiska, Aug 1943; (1 notebook) (Box 4)
- Casualty reports, 1945; (1 notebook) (Box 4)
- Field Order no. 1, Landing Force 168, 1 Aug 1943; (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Order of Battle, May 1944-Dec 1944 (Box 4)
- (1 folder)
- FSSF, Jumpmaster, (1 folder) (Box 5)
- FSSF, Organization Chart, (1 folder) (Box 5)
- FSSF, Organization Chart, (1 folder) (Box 5)
- Operation Buffalo, May 1944; (4 folders) (Box 5)
- Equipment, 24's, Aug -Sept 1943; (1 envelope) (Box 5)
- Fifth Army G-2 Reports, 17 Feb-15 Mar 1944; (6 folders) (Box 5)
- Kiska, Signal communications, (3 folders with many pamphlets) (Box 6)
- FSSF Historical Report, Feb-Dec 1944; (1 folder) (Box 6)
- Fifth Army - G-2 Daily Reports, 16 Mar -1 May 1944; (8 folders) (Box 6)
- History FSSF., (1 folder) (Box 7)
- Awards, requests for officers, movement orders, 1942-1943 (Box 7)
- FSSF - Special list of clothing and equipment S.24, 1943; (1 item. 42 p.) (Box 7)
- Operation plan no. 4-43 Task Force 16 Adak, Alaska., (1 item of many parts.) (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous lessons learned, Mar-Apr 1944; (1 folder) (Box 7)
- Organization Table of Organization and Equipment, Feb-May 1945; (2 folders) (Box 7)
- History file, 1943-1944, (1 folder) (Box 7)
- Secret Correspondence, Force, July 1942-April 1944; (1 folder) (Box 7)
- FSSF S-2 reports, Feb 1944; (2 folders) (Box 8)
- II Corps G-2 reports, June 1944; (2 folders) (Box 8)
- S-3 Journal Radicosa, (1 folder) (Box 8)
- France, map (Box 8)
- Captured enemy field order, South France, 27 Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Kiska - field orders other units, Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- FSSF Kiska Field Order 5, 8 Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- FSSF Kiska Field Order 5, Landing Force 16.8, 8 Aug 1944; (2 folders) (Box 8)
- MIS, BR, MA Studies, (1 folder) (Box 8)
- B. N. Hochcorn, 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Intelligence summaries, 1943-1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- At Mines (German data from Egypt), 1942-43; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- FSSF History (for possible use in history)., (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Agent Reports, 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Colonial file., (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Civil affairs South France, Aug-Dec 1944; (1 folder) (Box 8)
- Operations file, 1943-1944; (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Regimental Movement Plan, 1945; (2 folder) (Box 9)
- FSSF S-2 Reports., Jan, Mar-Jun, 1944; (7 folders) (Box 9)
- Directive, 16589; (1 folder) (Box 9)
- TUSA, Letters, memos, circulars, bulletins, 1944-1945; (2 folder) (Box 10)
- Third U.S. Army Administrative order #2 and changes 1 to 10, 1944-1945; (2 folder) (Box 10)
- TUSA, G-2 reports, 1945; (1 folder) (Box 10)
- TUSA, G-3 reports, 1944-1945; (1 folder) (Box 10)
- Reorganization A.R. Force Table of Organization and Equipment, (1 folder) (Box 10)
- Osforce (Apostle) operations plan, (1 folder) (Box 10)
- S-3 journal Anzioca, 30 Jan 1944 to 22 May 1944; (3 folders) (Box 11)
- Passenger List, (1 folder) (Box 11)
- Guerrilla Mission, (3 folders) (Box 11)
- Discipline, (1 folder) (Box 11)
- Nightlight, (2 folders) (Box 11)
- Plans and training, intelligence, (3 folders) (Box 11)
- S-3 Periodic reports, circa 22 Dec 1943 to 10 May 1944; (3 folders) (Box 12)
- Operation Grasshopper and Turtle, (2 folders) (Box 12)
- S-3 Journal Romeca, 22 May 1944 to 8 June 1944; (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Task Force Whitney, (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Training file #1, (1 envelope) (Box 12)
- German people's army, Guerrilla warfare, (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Table of Organization and Equipment, Infantry regiment, (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Infantry regiment, Table of Organization, (1 folder) (Box 12)
- Equipment, (2 folder) (Box 13)
- VI Corp G-2 reports, May 1944; (2 folders) (Box 13)
- Western naval task force, 1944; (1 folder) (Box 13)
- FSSF field orders, Part II, 1944; (4 folders) (Box 13)
- S-3 Journal Digensa, 1-10 Dec 1943; (1 folder) (Box 13)
- S-2 Operation Buffalo, (2 folder) (Box 14)
- S-2 Operation Turtle, (1 folder) (Box 14)
- S-2 Operation Grasshopper, (1 folder) (Box 14)
- S-2 Correspondence, 1943-1944; (2 folders) (Box 14)
- S-3 Journal Kiska, 13-24 Aug 1943; (1 folder) (Box 14)
- FSSF G O #8, 9, documentary evidence, GO #10 evidence, (3 folders) (Box 14)
- Organization Charts FSSF, (1 folder) (Box 14)
- Journal, Second operation, 21 Dec 1943-19 Jan 1944; (1 envelope) (Box 14)
- FSSF Original Table of Organization and Equipment, (1 envelope) (Box 14)
- German Forces, Group of photostats (Box 14)
- Bulletin of judge advocate general of the Army, Nov 1944; (1 document) (Box 14)
- Gazetteer of Western Germany, (1 booklet) (Box 14)
- SHAEF Weekly Intelligence summary, Apr 1945; (1 booklet) (Box 14)
- Regimental Administration, (1 folder) (Box 14)
- Equipment Losses, Italy, Oct -Dec 1943; (1 envelope) (Box 14)
- FSSF tentative tables of organization, Combat echelon, N19, 1942., (1 item) (Box 14)
- Head Quarters, Allied Land Forces, Norway, telephone directory (Box 14)
- S-3 periodic reports, 24 May to 28 Nov 1944; (3 folders) (Box 15)
- Award recommendations, (3 folders) (Box 15)
- The German People's Army, (1 folder) (Box 15)
- German People's Army with secret addenda, (1 folder) (Box 15)
- Fifth Army History, II, 115 p., III 135 p., undated (Box 15)
- S-3 Field Orders no. 1 to no. 28, (3 folders) (Box 16)
- II Corps Daily G-2 Reports, Dec 1943-Feb 1944; (4 folders) (Box 16)
- Maps/Report of Operations, (2 folders) (Box 16)
- Message Books. M-210 Signal Corps U.S. Army, (4 books) (Box 17)
- Operation Grasshopper, 16193; (1 folder) (Box 17)
- Miscellanea, (1 folder) (Box 17)
- FSSF S-2 Reports, Nov-Dec 1943; Aug-Nov 1944; (7 folders) (Box 17)
- Fifth Army, G-2 reports, 19 Nov -18 Dec 1943; (3 folders) (Box 17)
- S-3 Journal, Southern France, 8 Aug -30 Sept 1944; (3 folders) (Box 18)
- FSSF II corps G-2 reports, 19 Nov -19 Dec 1943; (2 envelope) (Box 18)
- Rough draft history, (1 folder) (Box 18)
- Force History, narrative notes, (2 folder) (Box 19)
- Receipts for documents, (1 folder) (Box 19)
- Patrol Reports, Feb -Oct 1944; (2 folders) (Box 19)
- British and Canadian correspondence, 9 June 1943-28 June 1944; (1 folder) (Box 19)
- Table of organization History, 1942-1944; (1 folder) (Box 19)
- Manuscript draft letters, (1 tablet) (Box 19)
- Gazetteers of France, Belgium, 1944; (1 book) (Box 19)
- Awards, 1944-1945; (1 folder) (Box 19)
- Surgeons' reports, action at Mt. La Difensa Italy, 3-9 Dec 1943; (1 folder) (Box 19)
- Radicosa, Mt. Majo, Operation reports, 1943-1944; (2 folders) (Box 20)
- 3rd Regt. report, (1 envelope) (Box 20)
- Regimental patrol reports, May 1944 Italy; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- Operation X, Italy, 1944; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- FSSF II corps G-2 reports, 1-14 Jan 1944; (2 envelope) (Box 20)
- FSSF S-3 Journal. Special orders, 1943-1945; (2 folders) (Box 20)
- Map, France Southern coast (Box 20)
- Cluster parachutes handbook, 1943 (Box 20)
- Operations, 21 Dec 1943 - 18 Jan 1944; (2 folders) (Box 20)
- Becket Mission to Rome, May 1944; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- Southern France, Prince Henry Loading Plan, Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- 7th Army miscellaneous, June-Aug 1944; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- Engraver's plates, war scenes (Box 20)
- Movement Orders Secret Travel Orders, U.S. to Italy, 1942-1943; (2 folders) (Box 20)
- Raid on Dieppe, 19 Aug 1942; (1 folder) (Box 20)
- Mount La Difensa Operation, circa 2-9 Dec 1943; (2 folders) (Box 21)
- Field order #1, Operation Anvil, July 1944; (3 folders) (Box 21)
- Awards, 1944-1945; (1 folder) (Box 21)
- Secret Security Field Order #1.,Landing Force 16.8, 1 Aug 1943; (2 folder) (Box 21)
- S-3 Journal, Southern France, circa 1 Oct-28 Nov 1944, 31 Dec 1944; (4 folder) (Box 22)
- Anzio, Rome Field Operations Periodic Reports, May 1944; (1 folder) (Box 22)
- Raid reports, Anzio., (1 folder) (Box 22)
- Kiska Operation, Field Orders (Box 22)
- D-Day on Levant, Battle Summary (Box 22)
- Intelligence Summaries of Enemy Operations, Central Europe and Norway, April-June 1945 (Box 22)
- FSSF Organizational Chart and Personnel Orders and Regulations (Box 22)
- Printed matter: U.S. Army Handbooks, Pamphlets, News Clippings (Box 22)
- Correspondence relating to publication of book (Box 22)
- Insignia patches (Box 22)
- Action on Attu, (1 item 102 p. +) (Box 23)
- Maps relating to FSSF Operations, (6 folders) (Box 23)
- Negatives (3x5) and Contact Prints in labelled negative jackets relating to the activities of the FSSF (Box 24-25)
- Negatives (35mm), 12 rolls (Box 24-25)
- Safety Film (Box 24-25)
- Intelligence Reports Circulation 1st Special Service Force, (1 folder) (Box 26)
- Gazetteer of Western Germany Map Series, (1 folder) (Box 26)
- Map of Italy, (1 folder) (Box 26)
- Bruno S-2 File, (2 folders) (Box 26)
- Tactics of the German Army and How to Defeat Them, (1 folder) (Box 26)
- Fifth Army G-2 Report, (4 folders) (Box 27)
- IV Corps G-2 Reports, 1-29 Feb 1944; (3 folders) (Box 27)
- IV Corps G-2 Reports, 1-30 April 1994; (3 folders) (Box 27)
- German Arms and Ammunition., (4 folders) (Box 28)
- Office of Prodaction Management, Springfield, Mass, A.D. Dickinson, (1 folder) (Box 28)
- Colonel E.A. Walker Operations File, (1 folder) (Box 28)
- Force History-Awards, Notes on Personal Experiences, La Difensa, Mt Majo, etc., (1 folder) (Box 28)
- Awards, (6 folders) (Box 29)
- Notes on Geographical Section General Staff Maps, (1 folder) (Box 29)
- Fifth Army History Vol. I., (1 folder) (Box 29)
- Southern France, 5 Aug -28 Nov 1994; (1 folder) (Box 29)
- Littoria City Plan, (1 folder) (Box 29)
- Printed Matter, The Saturday Evening Post, 1946; (1 folder) (Box 29)
- Miscellaneous Letters, commendations, (1 folder) (Box 29)
- VI Corps, (1 folder) (Box 30)
- General Frederick file, task file "B" and miscellaneous plans, (1 folder) (Box 30)
- Lessons from the Indian campaign, 10 March 1944; (1 folder) (Box 30)
- 5th Army G-2 Reports, May 1944; (4 folders) (Box 30)
- Amphibious Force, Atlantic Fleet, (1 folder) (Box 30)
- Intelligence Training, (1 folder) (Box 30)
- Infantry in Battle, (1 book) (Box 30)
- German Field Service Regulations, (1 book) (Box 30)
- Notes on Geographical Section General Staff Maps of Germany, Mar 1944; (1 folder) (Box 31)
- Training Data, Intelligence School, (3 folders) (Box 31)
- The Libyan Campaign, May 27-July 27, 1942; (1 folder) (Box 31)
- VI Corp, (4 folders) (Box 31)
- Maps (Box 32-33)
- Fifth Army, (7 folders) (Box 34)
- Photographs
  - 1000 4"x5" and 35 mm negatives of photos showing the activities of the First Special Service Force and the 474th Infantry during World War II in Europe, undated (Boxes 24-25)
  - 4 portrait photos of Major General Robert T. Frederick and others; 45 prints of the 474th Infantry in Normandy and Norway; 107 prints of the 474th Infantry at award formations, parades, and social events; 330 prints of combat scenes involving the 474th Infantry; 98 prints of the First Special Service Force in Italy and Southern France; and 87 unidentified aerial photographs, undated (Envelopes A-I)
  - 100 aerial photos of Kiska Island (Aleutians), M. La difensa (Italy), M. La Remetanea (Italy), and M. Maggiore (Italy), undated (Boxes 35-37)
    Scope and Contents note
    Formerly envelope mJ. Includes unidentified photos.
  - 103 prints of the First Special Service Force in Italy, undated (Envelope mK)
    Includes 1 print of the 474th Infantry in Norway.